Hey guys, in this video I'll be telling
you
how to do this AP Physics 2 question.
A small ball of mass 200 grams and charge
mu coulombs, so this would be equal to 6.0
times
10 to the negative 6 coulombs, this would
be
0.2 kilograms, is initially suspended
vertically
by a massless and inaccessible string of
length
50 centimetres, which is 0.5 metres.
Sometime later, a strong uniform external
electric
field, E, is switched on, and the ball
swings
to a maximum height where the string makes
a
45 degree angle with the vertical as shown
in
the figure above, so theta equals 45
degrees,
or pi over 4 radians.
So, first of all, what the question wants
you
to do is find the gravitational potential
energy
gained by the ball. So, the question asks
you
for delta U. We know that delta U is force
times distance, force is mg, distance is
delta
h, because we're talking about the
gravitational
potential energy, and we need to find, we
have
mass, we have gravity, we need to find
delta
h. Delta h is the vertical distance gained
by
the ball, so this would be delta h.
We know, let's call this side L, the
length,
so this would be L. If this is L, then,
and this is 45 degrees, then this would
also
be 45 degrees because these two are
parallel,
and so therefore this side length would be
considered
L times cosine of 45.
Now, L cosine 45 degrees plus
delta h would be equal to L, so delta h
would
be equal to L minus L cosine of 45
degrees,
delta h would be equal to L times 1 minus
cosine
of 45 degrees. So, now
we have delta h, we have mass, we have
gravity,
we can plug in the numbers, and this is
really
easy to do. Mass would be 0.2, gravity
9.81,
or 10, if you want, and then we have delta
h,
L is 0.5, 50 centimetres is 0.5 metres, 1
minus cosine of 45 degrees.
This is root 2 over 2.
When you plug in all the numbers, 0.2, you
would
get delta u g would be equal to 0.287
joules. That would be your final answer.
Okay, this is pretty straightforward.
Number b, using the law of conservation of
energy,
this should be learned in AP Physics 1,
find
the magnitude of the electric field, so we
have
to find the magnitude, which is the
absolute
value, and you can ignore air resistance.
So, the law of conservation of energy
states
that the net work done is equal to the
change
in energy of a system. So, the net
external
work done would be the change in energy of
the
system, which in this case, the system
would
be the ball and it would be the Earth.
So, we know that the work would be equal
to
force times distance. In this case, we're
talking
about horizontal distance.
So, the force would be Fq, the force of
the
electric field, times the horizontal
distance,
here to here. This is really easy to
calculate.
We know that this is L, so this length
here,
this length here, would be L sine of 45
degrees,
opposite over hypotenuse, or
pi over 4, if you're used to ratings.
Now, we know that the net energy done on
the
system would be equal to the change in
potential
energy plus the change in kinetic energy.
However, we see that over here, the ball
is
not moving, so the kinetic energy would be
equal
to zero. At the start, the ball is also
not
moving, so kinetic energy is also equal to
zero.
So, in this case, delta k would be equal
to
zero. So, what we're left with is Fq
L sine of 45 degrees equals delta ug,
which
we have calculated over here. The force is
equal
to the charge times electric field. So,
charge
times electric field, which is what we
need
to solve here, and L sine 45 delta ug.
Isolate for the electric field.
So, E would be equal to delta ug over Q
times L sine of 45 degrees.
E would be equal to 0.287 over, we
know that the charge is 6.0 times 10 to
the
negative 6 times 0.5
times root 2 over 2, which is sine of 45
degrees.
When you plug this in, you will get around
1.35
times 10 to the negative 5, and this is
measured
in electric field, so it would be newtons
per
coulomb. That would be your final answer.